Finding Aid for the Collection of Research Materials Related to Linguistic-Psychological Studies of Genie (pseudonym), 1895-2003, 1970-2003 LSC.0800
UCLA Library Special Collections
- 1. Audio visual materials, 1970-1993 (bulk 1970-1975); 44 boxes, 2 shoeboxes, and 2 oversize boxes
  - 1B. VHS cassettes, 1970-1977; 6.5 boxes
    - WGBH reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 70 (?), 1971 May 5 (Box 38, Folder 4)
      Genie is ill; refuses chocolate and throws it away; mother's visit to rehabilitation room in CHLA; tantrum because not allowed outside.
    - WGBH reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 117, 1972 February 18 (Box 38, Folder 5)
      Genie with Dave Rabb at JCC gymnasium.
    - WGBH reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 419, 1975 May 2 (Box 38, Folder 6)
      Genie and Baby Cory, eating cereal; electrodes.
    - WGBH video of Larry Solow and Genie working with sign, ca. 1975 (Box 38, Folder 7)
      Unknown 1/2" tape source.
    - WGBH video of Genie with janitor, no date (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape nos. 16, 24, 141, 142, 1971-1973 (Box 38, Folder 9)
      Reel-to-reel transfer. See Subseries 1A. 1/2" video tapes for the descriptive titles of these reels.
    - Duplicate reference copy of 1/2" tape nos. 16, 24, 141 and 142, 1971-1973 (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape nos. 134, 140, 176 and 183, 1972-1973 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape nos. 79, 86, 87 and 96, 1971 May-August (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Duplicate reference copy of 1/2" tape nos. 79, 86, 87 and 96, 1972 May-August (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 23, 1971 January 20 (Box 39, Folder 4)
      Meeting Liz; cobweb.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 24 (?), 1971 January 21 (Box 39, Folder 5)
      Leiter test with David Rigler.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 34, 1971 February 4 (Box 39, Folder 6)
      Outdoors; Jack Block and Jeanne H. Block.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 35, 1971 February 5 (Box 39, Folder 7)
      Jack Block and Jeanne H. Block; second attempt at pointing (unsuccessful), Genie ends by pointing with chin; balloons and gifts.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 45, 1971 March 2 (Box 39, Folder 8)
      Parquetry blocks; puzzles.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 53, 1971 March 15 (Box 39, Folder 9)
      Wagon; tantrum; Jay Shurley.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 64, 1971 April 6 (Box 39, Folder 10)
      With rabbit at rehabilitation; gardening; waiting for David Rigler and going outside.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 78, 1971 May 21, 24 (Box 40, Folder 1)
      Ironing Marilyn Rigler's dress; getting dressed to go out; tantrum in closet.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 79, 1971 May 24 (Box 40, Folder 2)
      Jean Butler's home.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 87, 1971 July 11-12 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 88, 1971 July 13 (Box 40, Folder 4)
      Jean Butler's home; eating, playing, in the kitchen. See index in box 1 for detailed description.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 91, 1971 July 19 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 92, 1971 July 21 (Box 40, Folder 6)
      Morning water play; eating lunch; this video follows a nearly sleepless night.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 93, 1971 July 22 (Box 40, Folder 7)
      Tree cutting.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 94, 1971 July 28-29 (Box 40, Folder 8)
      Toy, dog; washer and dryer installed; Roto Rooter.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 94, continued, 1971 July 28-29 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 96, 1971 August 18 (Box 40, Folder 10)
      Genie touches the Riglers' dog, Tory. See index in box 1 for detailed description.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 98, 1971 August 19, 21 (Box 41, Folder 1)
      Visit of James Kent; Genie making bracelets and chains with pipe cleaners.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 98, continued, 1971 August 19, 21 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 102, 1971 August 30; September 12-13 (Box 41, Folder 3)
      Block play; linguistic tests; alphabet letters.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 105, 1971 September 28; October 7, 12 (Box 41, Folder 4)
      Exercises with Marcia; portions of tantrum during evening; recognizing the names of foods with Reba Braff and Marilyn Rigler.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 105, continued, 1971 September 28; October 7, 12 (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 112, 1972 January 17, 18 (Box 41, Folder 6)
      Prepare for sleep EEG test.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 113, 1972 January 19 (Box 41, Folder 7)
      Genie with Susan Curtiss and Marilyn Rigler doing the hokey-pokey; Genie makes a sandwich.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 114, 1972 January 22 (Box 41, Folder 8)
      Marilyn Rigler and Genie making play dough. See index in box 1 for detailed description.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 114, continued, 1972 January 22 (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 122, 1972 July 2, 4 (Box 41, Folder 10)
      Trip to cabin with family; exploring; speech therapy with Reba Braff; Caroline reading a story; Caroline spilled Genie's box of beads and Genie reacts with anger.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 122, continued, 1972 July 2, 4 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 123, 1972 July 4, 14 (Box 42, Folder 2)
      Continuation of Genie's reaction to spilt beads; Genie with others at IHM school.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 137, 1972 November 9 (Box 42, Folder 3)
      Genie watching David Rigler assemble toy stove.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 141, 1973 February 7, 20; March 13, 24 (Box 42, Folder 4)
      Susan Curtiss linguistic testing; waiting for the school bus; loading the dishwasher; at Wiley house, exploring, eating lunch.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 147, 1973 May 25 (Box 42, Folder 5)
      Genie and Marilyn Rigler work at CHLA office; verbal rep. to pictures; "reading" action words; draws picture; listening to story.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 149, 1973 June 4 (Box 42, Folder 6)
      With Susan Curtiss at CHLA office, making questions and prepositions.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 150, 1973 June 4 (Box 42, Folder 7)
      Continuation at CHLA with Susan Curtiss; review session.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 154, 1973 June 21, July 11 (Box 42, Folder 8)
      At the Riglers; spontaneous drawing; in the kitchen before school; feeling sad and agitated.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 162, 1973 July 16 (Box 42, Folder 9)
      With Marilyn Rigler at CHLA office; skin brushes, exercises, rhythm.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 170, 1973 August 27 (Box 42, Folder 10)
      With Susan Curtiss at CHLA office, following tantrum.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 171, 1973 September 17 (Box 43, Folder 1)
      Short session with Jessalee. Session with Susan Curtiss; new task; using "no" and "not"; forming answers on pocket board.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 179, 1973 November 21 (Box 43, Folder 2)
      In the kitchen, before school. Discussing Christmas; coping with delay in gratification. Susan Curtiss administers Furth Form test.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 181, 1973 November 28 (Box 43, Folder 3)
      With Susan Curtiss at the CHLA office; looking at semantic features.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 189, 1974 January 2 (Box 43, Folder 4)
      Susan Curtiss tests using selected items from Auditory Test for Language Comprehension (an aphasia test); conjunction, disjunction comprehension, comparative and superlative, and relational terms.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 193, 1974 January 17 (Box 43, Folder 5)
      Making pudding; Marilyn pretends to be mama, Genie pretends to be the baby. Marilyn feeds Genie cereal. Additional description: "Genie has for some time been very interested in the Mixmaster. Marilyn Rigler has tried to channel this interest in a functional way."
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 222, 1974 April 18 (Box 43, Folder 6)
      Larry Solow teaches Genie to sign; Genie's birthday.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 223, 1974 April 23-24 (Box 43, Folder 7)
      Genie mixing pudding; Susan Curtiss playing piano while Genie listens.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 227, 1974 June 21 (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 412, 1977 June 20 (Box 43, Folder 9)
      Genie at CHLA office; Marilyn Rigler.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 417, 1977 June 24 (Box 43, Folder 10)
      Therapy session with the Riglers, focused on Genie's closed mouth and dentistry.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 424, 1977 January 15 (Box 44, Folder 1)
      Genie with the Riglers; dealing with vomiting.
    - Reference copy of 1/2" tape reel no. 437, 1977 April 30 (Box 44, Folder 2)
      At rehabilitation with David Rigler.
  - 1C. Mini DVCs and Hi8 P6-120HMP video, 1970-1977, 1992; 2 shoeboxes
    This subseries consists of 122 miniature digital video cassettes and two Hi8 videos. The DVCs were created by the Tokyo Broadcasting System in 2003 as a stipulation of their use of 1/2" tape reels, Super 8 mm films, and still photographs of Genie for a documentary television show entitled "3.8 Billion Years of Life: What is Man? Park IV." Most of the DVC tapes are numbered and correspond to the 1/2" tape reel numbers found in Subseries 1A. The 1/2" video tape reel numbers duplicated here include: 2-9, 11-13, 16-25, 27, 30, 41-44, 49-52, 54, 56, 59, 63, 65-69, 71, 73-86, 89-90, 92, 94, 98-101, 105-108, 112-113, 115-121, 127-190, 134-138, 140- 144, 149-150, 159, 164, 167, 172, 183-184, 214, 223, 228-229, 232-233, 237, 239-241, 402, 414, 417, 418-419, 421-423, 425-427, 432 and 436. Ten additional mini DVCs, stored in box 46, contain copies of unidentified 8mm film reels, an undated dental examination, and copies of the Hi8 video material. The two Hi8 video cassettes, also located in box 46, contain footage of Genie from December 1992.
    - 1970-1975, 1992 (Box 45, Box 46)
  - 1D. Super 8 mm film, 1970-1973; 1 oversize box
    This subseries consists of film footage of Genie, primarily taken by David or Marilyn Rigler. Footage includes outings and everyday activities at school and around the home. The reels were originally labeled by general subject content in David Rigler's handwriting; he also gave each reel a number, beginning with reel no. 12. His notations on the outside of the boxes were used to create the titles seen here in the finding aid. The Rigler numbers were also noted and retained during processing. All film is Super 8 mm Kodak Ektachrome stock, unless otherwise noted.
    - No reel number given, no date (Box 47, Folder 1)
      Genie and Marilyn Rigler; Genie in her room and in the kitchen; taking a bath; doll house therapy; Rigler parents; eye exam.
    - No reel number given, 1970 June 26 (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - Reel no. 12, 1972 September 24; October 11 (Box 47, Folder 3)
      Bath; David Rigler.
    - Reel no. 13, 1973 March 2-3 (Box 47, Folder 4)
      Carillo camping trip; fun at table by lantern light; getting a pan of water.
    - Reel no. 14, 1973 April 6 (Box 47, Folder 5)
      Genie's birthday at school.
    - Reel no. 15, 1973 April 6 (Box 47, Folder 6)
    - Reel no. 16, 1973 March 23 (Box 47, Folder 7)
      Snow at Big Bear cabin; Father Al is planning board; self stimulation mannerisms; in bathroom making faces; school bus, Mr. James; camping at Leo Carillo.
    - Reel no. 17, 1973 March 24 (Box 47, Folder 8)
      Genie listening to Camino Barono record; in bathtub; at mother's house.
    - Reel no. 19, 1973 February 15 (Box 47, Folder 9)
      Genie at school; eating lunch and on playground.
    - Reel no. 20, 1972 October 31; November 21 (Box 47, Folder 10)
      Gym trampoline; tantrum.
    - Reel no. 21, 1972 March (Box 47, Folder 11)
      Genie in bath with soap suds; "waves not hurt"; eye exam.
    - Reel no. 22, no date (Box 47, Folder 12)
      Seals at the zoo; Genie in pool.
    - Reel no. 23, 1972 April 13 (Box 47, Folder 13)
      Genie with diver's mask; cutting toenails.
    - Reel no. 24, 1973 February 10-15 (Box 47, Folder 14)
      Genie in park with horses; at school.
    - Reel no. 25, 1973 March 3 (Box 47, Folder 15)
      Leo Carillo camping trip; playing with bucket of water; walking; tantrum on beach; kicking shoes.
    - Reel no. 26, no date (Box 47, Folder 16)
      E. D. Raleb (?); somersaults; jumping.
    - Reel no. 27, no date (Box 47, Folder 17)
      IHM school; beach.
    - Reel no. 28, 1972 October 28 (Box 47, Folder 18)
      Bisons, horses, zebras, and giraffes at the zoo.
    - Reel no. 29, 1972 June (Box 47, Folder 19)
      Genie gets a toy truck; tantrum; puzzle lesson in kitchen; putting drops in ears.
    - Reel no. 30, 1973 March 15, 20, 31; April 1 (Box 47, Folder 20)
      Chocolate pudding; boarding school bus; school; train ride at the park; zoo.
    - Reel no. 31, ca. 1973 February 29; March 1 (Box 47, Folder 21)
      Genie eating breakfast and loading dishwasher; porch test; washing hour in bath; Santa Monica, Marina Del Rey with dog and grandparents; in bath masturbating with boat.
    - Reel no. 32, 1970 November 25 (Box 47, Folder 22)
      Magic show.
    - Reel no. 33, 1970 December; 1971 January (Box 47, Folder 23)
      First half Wiley back yard; Genie's birthday party at Rehabilitation center.
    - Reel no. 34, 1973 January 30 (Box 47, Folder 24)
      Crystal climbers.
    - Reel no. 35, 1973 February 19 (Box 47, Folder 25)
      School; Big Bear snow and cabin.
    - Reel no. 36, 1972 December 25; 1973 January 30 (Box 47, Folder 26)
      Home with mother; Crystal Climbers.
    - Reel no. 37, 1972 July 17 (Box 47, Folder 27)
      Genie at beach; dancing; additional content (illegible).
    - Reel no. 38, 1972 July (Box 47, Folder 28)
      Genie playing in bath; at school.
    - Reel no. 39, 1972 May-June (Box 47, Folder 29)
      Looking at fireplace; playing with ball with Natalie; working out on exercises; IHM school in early June.
    - Reel no. 40, 1972 October 24 (Box 47, Folder 30)
      Swimming.
    - Reel no. 41, 1972 October (Box 47, Folder 31)
      Rope swinging; trampoline.
    - Reel no. 42, 1972 December 25 (Box 47, Folder 32)
      Genie at home for first visit.
    - Reel no. 43, 1972 March (Box 47, Folder 33)
      Eye exam; bike for life; tantrum; Mark and Brenda; Genie in gym.
    - Reel no. 44, 1970 January (Box 47, Folder 34)
      No description given. Kodak Kodachrome film.
    - Reel no. 45, 1972 April, May 10 (Box 47, Folder 35)
      Genie with Reba Braff; making eggs; in bath.
    - Reel no. 46, 1972 March 20, 24, 25 (Box 47, Folder 36)
      Genie in gym; June Wood; Genie at zoo.
    - Reel no. 47, 1973 April 1 (Box 47, Folder 37)
      Genie and Marilyn Rigler at the zoo.
    - Reel no. 48, no date (Box 47, Folder 38)
      Genie listening to music; Michael and dog; bathtub; toenail cutting; train.
    - Reel no. 49, no date (Box 47, Folder 39)
      Chimpanzees and gorilla at the zoo.
    - Reel no. 50, 1973 (Box 47, Folder 40)
      At beach camping trip, listening to record.
    - Reel no. 51, no date (Box 47, Folder 41)
      Bus ride through zoo.
    - Reel no. 52, 1972 August (Box 47, Folder 42)
      Trampoline; throwing ball against wall; balloon; paddle supports; somersaults; ladder.
  - 1E. Audio materials, 1970-1975, 1993; 1 oversize box
    This subseries consists of audio recordings and audio cassette tapes relating to Genie. The audio reels include: one 3 1/2" reel of an interview with Stephanie Heinzmann, DPSS employee, dated 1970 December 8; two 3 1/2" reels of meetings attended by the Kirks, Jean Butler, David Rigler, H. Hansen, and James Kent dated 1972 February 2; six 7" reels dated 1972 November 7-12; one 3 1/2" reel labeled "Conference with Block, Hansen, Kent, Rigler, 1975 February 24"; and four unidentified reels. Audio cassette tapes include: one tape labeled "Conference with Genie's teacher, 1973 March 28"; one tape labeled "Rymer, NPR Fresh Air, 1993 April 9."
    - 1970-1975, 1993 (Box 48)
- 2. Conference papers, essays and reports, 1968-1983
  This series is comprised of various conference papers, essays, and reports written by research team members and study consultants regarding their work with Genie or with related and applicable research topics. Photocopies of published journal articles generally related to child development, child psychology, and abuse were removed from the collection during processing. A bibliography of these materials is stored in the collection file and is available upon request.
  - Developmental and Clinical Aspects of Child Development Seminar--Various material, 1974 March 4 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    Access
    This file is open for research. Duplication is strictly prohibited.
  - Developmental and Clinical Aspects of Child Development Seminar--Various material, 1974 March 4 (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - Genie conference--Correspondence, 1972 August 10-1972 October 16 (Box 49, Folder 2)
    Informal conference held at the Children's Hospital of Los Angeles, September 22-23, 1972.
  - Genie conference--Various material, 1972 March 3-1972 October 9; undated (Box 49, Folder 3)
    Correspondence, and list of participants.
  - Genie conference--Various material, 1972 March 3 (Box 85, Folder 2)
  - Think In material, 1971 May 3-4 (Box 49, Folder 4)
    Includes various synopses on Genie's condition, including her state upon entering Childrens Hospital.
  - Think In material, 1971 (Box 85, Folder 3)
  - [Krashen], Steve--Draft article for submission to Language Learning, ca. 1973 April 17 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - [Krashen], Steve--Draft article for submission to Language Learning, 1973 April 17 (Box 85, Folder 4)
  - Abstract for paper submission to American Association of Psychiatric Services for Children, ca. 1976 February (Box 49, Folder 6)
    Title of paper: Quest for Autonomy in Genie: An unusual case study. Flash cards were attached to submission.
  - Abstract submission for "Protracted Isolation in Childhood: Study of Historic Case", 1973 May 22 (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - American Psychological Association--Various material related to paper presentations, 1972 January 6-1972 May 2 (Box 49, Folder 8)
    Correspondence and papers drafts.
  - American Psychological Association--Annual convention material, 1972 September (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - American Psychological Association - Annual Convention Material, 1972 September (Box 85, Folder 5)
  - American Speech and Hearing Association annual convention material, 1972 November 18-21 (Box 49, Folder 10)
    Contains papers presented at convention.
  - Battison, Robbin / Phonological deletion in American sign language, 1974 February (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - Battison, Robbin and Harry Markowicz / Sign aphasia and neurolinguistic theory, 1974 February (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - Bellugi-Klima, Ursula / Grammatical comprehension test, 1968 March (Box 49, Folder 13)
  - Braff, Reba G. / American Speech and Hearing Association, 1972 November (Box 49, Folder 14)
    Remarks prepared for the Annual Convention of the American Speech and Hearing Association, San Francisco, California.
  - Caspar Hauser research--Marilyn Rigler's notes, ca. 1975 (Box 49, Folder 15)
  - Caspar Hauser research--Notecards by Marilyn Rigler comparing parallels of Genie and Caspar Hauser, ca. 1975 (Box 49, Folder 16)
    Possibly notecards for speech or presentation.
  - Caspar Hauser research--Text by Marilyn Rigler comparing parallels of Genie and Caspar Hauser, ca. 1975 (Box 49, Folder 17)
    Possibly a script for a speech or presentation.
  - Clark, Eve V. / What's in a word? On the child's acquisition of semantics in his first language, 1971 August (Box 49, Folder 18)
    Paper presented at the Conference on Developmental Psycholinguistics, State University of New York at Buffalo, Buffalo, N.Y.
  - Correspondence--Baumrind, Diana, 1972 August 14 (Box 49, Folder 19)
    To David Rigler. Also includes Rigler's response.
  - Correspondence--Goolishian, Harold A., 1976 May 1 (Box 49, Folder 20)
    To David Rigler regarding paper presentation rejection.
  - Correspondence--Kennell, John H., 1973 October 30 (Box 49, Folder 21)
    To David Rigler regarding presentations in Washington and Chicago.
  - Correspondence--Macken, Marlys A., 1972 November 22 (Box 49, Folder 22)
    To Victoria Fromkin regarding Child Language Research Forum.
  - Correspondence--Regarding "Extreme Psychosocial Deprivation" symposium, 1971 May 12-1972 June 7 (Box 49, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence--Rigler, David, 1972 April 14 (Box 49, Folder 24)
    To Diana Baumrind
  - Correspondence--Rigler, David, 1976 August 4-October 21 (Box 49, Folder 25)
    Various recipients regarding paper presentations.
  - Correspondence--Shurley, Jay, 1972 June 15 (Box 49, Folder 26)
    Copy of letter to Dr. Lee Sechrest.
  - Correspondence--Shurley, Jay, 1972 July 28 (Box 49, Folder 27)
    To Diane Baumrind regarding paper for APA symposium.
  - Curtiss, Susan, et al / An update on the linguistic development of Genie, 1975 March 13-15 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    Paper presented at the 26th Annual Georgetown Round Table by Victoria Fromkin.
  - Curtiss, Susan, et al / Case of Genie: an update on her linguistic development-some questions, some answers, 1973 December (Box 50, Folder 2)
    Paper presented at the winter meeting of the Linguistic Society of America.
  - Curtiss, Susan, et al / Case of Genie: some questions, some answers, ca. 1973 December (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Curtiss, Susan, et al / Language acquisition after the critical period: Genie as of April 1973, 1973 April (Box 50, Folder 4)
    Paper presented at the Ninth Annual Meeting of the Chicago Linguistic Society
  - Curtiss, Susan, et al / Linguistic development of Genie, 1973 September 18 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    Includes letter to Victoria Fromkin noting the acceptance of the manuscript for publication in Language journal.
  - Curtiss, Susan, et al / Linguistic development of Genie, 1974 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    Language 50 (3): 528-554.
  - Ephemera--Conference schedule for paper presentation, 1976 June 14-16 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    Presentation at American Association for the Advancement of Science at University of Montana.
  - Ephemera--List of participants for XXth International Congress of Psychology, 1972 August 13-19 (Box 50, Folder 8)
  - Feldman, Heidi and Susan Goldin Meadow / Spontaneous generation of language: the study of deaf children of hearing parents, 1973 October (Box 50, Folder 9)
  - Friedlander, Bernard Z. / Receptive language development in infancy: issues and problems, 1970 (Box 50, Folder 10)
  - Fromkin, Victoria, et al / Development of language in Genie: a case of language acquisition beyond the 'critical period', 1974 (Box 50, Folder 11)
    Brain and Language 1, 81-107.
  - Hansen, Howard / First experiences and the emergence of "Genie", 1972 September 1-8 (Box 50, Folder 12)
    Presented at the 80th Annual Convention of the American Psychological Association, Honolulu, Hawaii.
  - Hansen, Howard / Genesis of the tragedy, 1972 January 26 (Box 50, Folder 13)
    One-page overview of the Genie's background.
  - Hearn, Sharon / Year of reading instruction with Genie, 1974 Fall (Box 50, Folder 14)
  - Hewes, Gordon W. / An explicit formulation of the relationship between tool-using, tool-making and the emergence of language, ca. 1972 (Box 50, Folder 15)
  - Kent, James T. / Eight months in the hospital, 1972 September 1-8 (Box 50, Folder 16)